Guide to the Mary Burnett Horton Papers MC.222
New York University Archives
Mary Burnett Horton Papers
1936-1975
1939-1974
New York University Archives
Horton, Mary Burnett
MC.222
11 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
Mary Burnett Horton was an authority in home economics and a pioneer in consumer and institutional education in the food and nutrition field. She received a master's degree from NYU in 1946 and worked as a bacteriologist and as head of the consumer education program at Sheffield Farms before being appointed director of the National Dairy's Sealtest Consumer Service where she worked until retiring in 1962. The collection consists of a large number of recipes in the form of books, booklets, brochures, circulars and clippings; food-related publications and printed materials; article drafts, speeches, notes, conference materials, photographs and personal and professional correspondence.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series, one of which has been further arranged into subseries. The contents of each series and subseries are arranged alphabetically. The series and subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I contains records relating to Horton's activities in Sheffield Farms, Sealtest and the food industry in general.
Series II contains Horton's personal correspondence, biographical information, work prospects and other miscellaneous materials.
Series III contains photographs of Mary Horton at various events, in her office, and of the facilities of Sheffield Farms and Sealtest Kitchens.
Series IV contains materials related to Horton's professional associations unrelated to the food industry, including her 1963 trip to the Soviet Union.
Series V, Subseries I contains recipe books.
Series V, Subseries II contains recipe booklets.
Series V, Subseries II contains loose recipes.
Missing Title
Food and Nutrition
Personal
Photographs
Professional
Recipes
Biography of Mary Burnett Horton
Mary Burnett Horton was born in Stirling, Scotland, in 1897 and moved to New York City with her family as a child. She graduated from Hunter College, where she trained as a bacteriologist. In 1920 she began working as a laboratory assistant at Sheffield Farms; she became chief bacteriologist in 1932. When Sheffield inaugurated a consumer education program in 1937, she became its director, developing school and public visiting programs at four major milk processing plants in greater New York, focusing on pasteurization and the nutrition of dairy products. With wartime restrictions in 1941, she took the programs to consumers, lecturing extensively to women's clubs on feeding families under food shortages and rationing. She served as chairperson of the Manhattan Nutrition Committee from 1944 to 1946, while earning a master's degree from New York University in Home Economics with a specialty in nutrition in 1946. In 1949 she became the only woman elected to the Board of Directors of Sheffield Farms, a post she held until 1956, when the company became a division of National Dairy.
In 1947 Horton was appointed director of National Dairy's Sealtest Consumer Service, which included four test kitchens equipped with the latest and newest appliances. The aim of the kitchens was to help consumers, dietitians, and school, hospital and industrial food managers to adjust to postwar changes, including the advent of convenience foods and the transfer of new technology to consumer products. The staff working in the kitchens performed extensive work on recipe development, culminating in recipe pamphlets, publicity releases and quantity recipe cards. During her fifteen years as director of Sealtest Consumer Service, Horton was widely regarded as an authority in home economics and a pioneer in the consumer and institutional education in the foods and nutrition field.
Mary Horton retired from Sealtest in 1962 but continued to be involved in various professional associations. In addition to her position at Sealtest, Mary Horton was the chairperson of New York City Home Economists in Business (1953), the American Home Economics Association, and the Consumer Services Committee of Grocery Manufacturers of America (1955-56). She served on the U.S. Navy Food Advisory Committee from 1948 to 1962. As consumer consultant editor of the trade publication Food Business from 1953 to 1963 she authored many articles in various publications.
Horton also served as the chairperson of civil service of the New York City Federation of Women's Clubs. She was appointed a member of the Women's Committee established in the late 1950s by Governor Rockefeller and the Department of Commerce whose purpose was to find ways to create careers for women. In 1963 she traveled to the Soviet Union as part of the American Home Economics Association to take part in a Women's Congress. Mary Horton died in 1974 at the age of 77.
Scope and Content
The collection documents the activities of Mary Horton in her role as a pioneer in the food field and consists of a large number of recipes in the form of books, booklets, brochures, circulars and clippings; food related publications and printed materials; article drafts, speeches, notes, conference materials, photographs and personal and professional correspondence.
Separated Materials
Memorabilia in the collection have been removed and are stored with the University Archives Memorabilia Collection. Please contact the University Archives for access to these materials.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Provenance
The collection was accessioned by University Archives in four accretions from 2009-2010.
Access Restrictions
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact New York University Archives, (212) 998-2641, university-archives@nyu.edu.
Food supply.; Food.; Universities and Colleges -- Alumni and alumnae.; Food industry and trade; Kraftco Corporation; Grocery Manufacturers of America; Sheffield Farms; National Dairy Products Corporation; American Home Economics Association; Sealtest, Inc.
- Series I: Food and Nutrition
  - American Home Department Lecture Announcement, 1943 March (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - American Public Health Association -- Nutrition Foundation, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles by Horton, 1947-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles on Horton, 1947-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chicken Festival, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Conventions and Events -- Miscellaneous, 1940-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Digests, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Drying and Freezing, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Food Additives -- Informational Guides, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Food Advisory Committee of the National Security Industrial Association, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Food Business Magazine, 1953-1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Food Business Magazine -- Oversize, 1955-1958 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Food Forum -- Notes, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Food -- Miscellaneous, 1944-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Grocery Manufacturers of America, 1 of 2, 1949-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Grocery Manufacturers of America, 2 of 2, 1950-1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Historic Data (Milk), 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Howdy Colonel Book, 1948-1962 (Box 6)
  - Informational Brochures, Pamphlets and Booklets, 1 of 2, 1959-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Informational Brochures, Pamphlets and Booklets, 2 of 2, 1957-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Massachusetts Home Economics Association -- Speech, May 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - McCormick's Map of the World, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings -- Oversize, 1942-1949 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1949-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - National Dairy Products -- Miscellaneous, 1947-1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Navy Cook Book Task Committee, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Navy Food Committee, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Publications -- Oversize, 1949-1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Recipe Drafts and Suggestions, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Resumes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Rochester Speech, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Sealtest Consumer Service Department, 1 of 3, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Sealtest Consumer Service Department, 2 of 3, 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Sealtest Consumer Service Department, 3 of 3, 1947-1962 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Sealtest Kitchens, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Sealtest Miscellaneous, 1936-1959 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Sealtest Notepads, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Sealtest Notes, Undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Sheffield Farms -- Miscellaneous, 1940-1948 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Sheffield Farms Publications (Anniversary), 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Sheffield News, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Sheffield News, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Sheffield News, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Sheffield News -- World War II Articles, Memos and Research, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Society of American Bacteriologists, 1944-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, 1 of 2, 1942-1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Speeches, 2 of 2, 1954-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Speeches and Articles, 1 of 2, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Speeches and Articles, 2 of 2, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Speeches -- Promotional Materials, Circa 1941-1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tuskegee Food and Nutrition Institute, 1 of 2, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Tuskegee Food and Nutrition Institute, 2 of 2, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - United States Naval Training Center Yearbook, 1949 (Box 6)
  - USDA, FDA and Consumer Regulation Materials, 1 of 2, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - USDA, FDA and Consumer Regulation Materials, 2 of 2, 1963-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - World War II Speeches, Presentations and Publicity, 1943-1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - World War II Presentations and Other Materials, 1938-1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series II: Personal
  - Biographical Information, 1949-1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Birthday Cards, 1963-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - British Colonial Empire Brochure, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, Circa 1940s - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence -- Condolences, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence -- Condolences and Follow-Up, 1 of 3, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence -- Condolences and Follow-Up, 2 of 3, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence -- Condolences and Follow-Up, 3 of 3, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence -- Retirement, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence -- Retirement Album, 1 of 2, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence -- Retirement Album, 2 of 2, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence -- Retirement Album (Oversize), 1962 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Expense Report, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Job Applications, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous Cards, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings -- Oversize, 1947-1965 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - New York University, 1946-1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - New York University Diploma, 1946 (Box 7)
  - Obituary Materials, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Travel Miscellaneous, Undated; 1949 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Vacation, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - War Ration Books, Circa 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Series III: Photographs
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Europe and Russia Trip (Slides) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip to London, Paris Vienna, Russia and Helsinki (Slides) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Events, 1 of 2, 1942-1960 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Events, 2 of 2, 1942-1960 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Food Editors Conference, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Navy Cookbook Task Committee, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Navy Food Committee, 1957-1961 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Navy Miscellaneous, 1956-1962 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Portraits, 1 of 2, 1941-1961 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Portraits, 2 of 2, 1949-1970 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Portraits (Early), Circa 1918-1935 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Sealtest Offices, Kitchens and Hospitality Center, 1948-1957 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Sheffield Farms, Circa 1939-1955 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Sheffield Farms -- Old Photos, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Professional
  - Advertising Women of New York Foundation -- Consumer Conference, 1 of 2, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Advertising Women of New York Foundation -- Consumer Conference, 2 of 2, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Alphi Delta Pi, Undated; 1974 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Alpha Delta Pi Convention, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip, 1 of 3, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip, 2 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip, 3 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Denmark) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Diary) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Lobster Bib) (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Paris Congress), 1963-1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Post Trip) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Russia), 1 of 2, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Russia), 2 of 2, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Russia Printed Material), 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Russia, Rose and Handkerchief), 2 of 2, Circa 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (WNYC Record), 1963 September 12; Record has not been digitized. (Box 5)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Women and Children in the USSR) (Box 7)
  - American Home Economics Association -- 1963 Trip (Your Trip to USSR), 1962 (Box 7)
  - Civil Service Reform Association, 1 of 2, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Civil Service Reform Association, 2 of 2, 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Civil Service Reform Association, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Home Economics and Home Makers Forum, 1947-1955 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Booklets, 1955-1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Home Economists in Business, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - National Civil Service League, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - New York Woman's Council, 1 of 2, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - New York Woman's Council, 2 of 2, 1961-1973 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - New York Woman's Council -- Conference on Women, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1924-1975 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Radio Broadcast, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 8, Cd ref237)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Record has been digitized. Only the access CD is available for use.
  - UNICEF, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Women's City Club of NY, Inc., 1962 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - World War II Miscellaneous, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Series V: Recipes
  - Books
    - 641 Tested Recipes from the Sealtest Kitchens, 1 of 2, 1954 (Box 7)
    - 641 Tested Recipes from the Sealtest Kitchens, 2 of 2, 1954 (Box 7)
    - 1001 Dairy Dishes from the Sealtest Kitchens, 1 of 2, 1963 (Box 7)
    - 1001 Dairy Dishes from the Sealtest Kitchens, 2 of 2, 1963 (Box 7)
    - A Date With A Dish, 1948; De Knight, Freda, 1910-1963 (Box 6)
    - Better Homes and Gardens New Cook Book, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Big Boy Barbecue Book, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Bottoms Up: Guide to Pleasant Drinking, Undated (Box 7)
    - Congressional Club Cook Book, The, 1961 (Box 6)
    - Complete Cheese Cookbook, The, 1971; Kraftco Corporation (Box 7)
    - Cooking the Smart Way, 1958; Flexner, Marion W., 1899-1992 (Box 6)
    - Cooking With Soup, Undated (Box 6)
    - Dairyland Cook Book, 1959 (Box 6)
    - Entertainingly Yours: A Buffet Cook Book, 1964; Rosen, Ruth Chier (Box 7)
    - Fast & Fancy Cookery, 1959; Cranwell, John Philips, 1904-1982 (Box 6)
    - Favorite Recipes from America's Dairyland, Undated (Box 5)
    - Favorite Recipes of America's Food Editors, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Favorite Recipes from the United Nations, 1960; American Home Economics Association (Box 7)
    - General Foods Kitchens Cookbook, The, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Good Housekeeping Cook Book, The, 1949; Marsh, Dorothy B. (Box 7)
    - Good Housekeeping Cook Book, 1955; Marsh, Dorothy B. (Box 6)
    - Gourmet Cookbook, The: Volume II, 1957; Gourmet International (Box 6)
    - Madison Avenue Cook Book, The, 1962; Koehler, Alan (Box 7)
    - Menu Maker and Party Planner, 1957; Tartan, Beth, 1919-1992 (Box 6)
    - New Ways to Gracious Living: Waring Blendor Cook Book, 1957; Schur, Sylvia (Box 7)
    - Peggy Put the Kettle On, 1951; Firmin, Blanche C. (Box 6)
    - Pyrex Prize Recipes, 1953 (Box 7)
    - Recipes Out of Bilibid, 1946; Fowler, Halstead C.; Wagner, Dorothy (Box 6)
    - Sealtest Food Adviser, 1936-1942 (Box 6)
    - Sealtest Food Adviser, 1943-1951 (Box 6)
    - Summer Cookbook, 1954; McCarroll, Marion Clyde (Box 6)
    - What to Cook for CompanyWhat to Cook for Company, 1952; Sullivan, Lenore (Box 6)
    - Woman's Day: Collector's Cook Book, 1960 (Box 6)
  - Booklets
    - 1940s Recipes, 1943-1949 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1950s Recipes, 1 of 8, 1950-1954 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 1950s Recipes, 2 of 8, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 1950s Recipes, 3 of 8, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 1950s Recipes, 4 of 8, 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - 1950s Recipes, 5 of 8, 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - 1950s Recipes, 6 of 8, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - 1950s Recipes, 7 of 8, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1950s Recipes, 8 of 8, 1952-1956 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - 1960s Recipes, 1 of 4 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1960s Recipes, 2 of 4, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1960s Recipes, 3 of 4, 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1960s Recipes, 4 of 4, 1965-1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1970s Recipes, 1 of 2, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1970s Recipes, 2 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Chicken Festival, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Sealtest, 1 of 3, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Sealtest, 2 of 3, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Sealtest, 3 of 3, 1943-1956 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Undated Recipes, 1 of 4 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Undated Recipes, 2 of 4 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Undated Recipes, 3 of 4 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Undated Recipes, 4 of 4 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Loose
    - 1940s Recipes, 1943-1949 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - 1950s Recipes, 1 of 3, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - 1950s Recipes, 2 of 3, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - 1950s Recipes, 3 of 3, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - 1950s Recipes -- Oversize, 1951-1959 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1960s Recipes, 1 of 3, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - 1960s Recipes, 2 of 3, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - 1960s Recipes, 3 of 3, 1960-1969 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - 1960s Recipes -- Oversize, 1 of 2, 1961-1968 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1960s Recipes -- Oversize, 2 of 2, 1960-1969 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 1970s Recipes, 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - 1970s Recipes -- Oversize, 1970-1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Betty Crocker Recipe Box, 1960-1971 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Binder I, 1 of 2, 1956-1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Binder I, 2 of 2, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Binder II, 1 of 3, 1957-1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Binder II, 2 of 3, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Binder II, 3 of 3, 1962-1969 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Binder II (Empty), Undated (Box 5)
    - Life Recipe Box, 1959 (Box 7)
    - Quantity Recipes from the Sealtest Kitchens Binder, Undated (Box 7)
    - Sealtest Recipes, 1 of 3, 1948-1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Sealtest Recipes, 2 of 3, 1948-1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Sealtest Recipes, 3 of 3, 1956-1962 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Undated Recipes, 1 of 4 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Undated Recipes, 2 of 4 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Undated Recipes, 3 of 4 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Undated Recipes, 4 of 4 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Undated Recipes -- Oversize (Box 9, Folder 6)